<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cure of cares or a short discourse, declaring the condition of worldly cares; with some remedies appropriated unto them Penned for the use of all, but is most proper for such as be distressed. By Henry Mason parson of S. Andrews Vndershaft London.</title>
            <author>Mason, Henry, 1573?-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838097</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2456</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07204)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2456)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1074:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cure of cares or a short discourse, declaring the condition of worldly cares; with some remedies appropriated unto them Penned for the use of all, but is most proper for such as be distressed. By Henry Mason parson of S. Andrews Vndershaft London.</title>
                  <author>Mason, Henry, 1573?-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M[iles] F[lesher] for Iohn Clarke, and are to be sold at his shop, under S. Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Contentment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Contentment --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2456:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2456:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CVRE OF CARES. OR A SHORT DISCOVRSE, declaring the condition of worldly Cares; with ſome Remedies appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated unto them.</p>
            <p>Penned for the uſe of all, but is moſt proper for ſuch as be diſtreſſed.</p>
            <p>BY HENRY MASON Parſon of <hi>S. Andrews Vnderſhaft London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for IOHN CLARKE, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop under S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:2456:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2456:2"/>
            <head>THE CVRE OF CARES. <hi>OR</hi> A ſhort Diſcourſe, declaring the condition of worldly Cares, with ſome remedies appropriated unto them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no man, I ſuppoſe, ſo happy, but may have ſome croſſes that may breed him <hi>cares,</hi> and ſome cares that may require a <hi>cure.</hi> For ſay that a man hath wealth, and honour, and autority, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of all things; ſo that neighbours, who looke upon his outward ſtate, do thinke him an happy man, and will ſay of him, that hee needeth not <hi>care;</hi> yet the ſame man lightly either hath an unquiet wife, or diſobedient children, or unfaithfull ſervants, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious neighbours, or unnaturall kinſmen; that do both wrong him and diſquiet him. Or if he be free from all theſe (as few men are,) yet the frowne of a Great man, or a loſſe in his eſtate, or a miſcariage in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2456:3"/>ſome ſuite, or one ſudden accident or other may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall him to his griefe. And as
<note n="a" place="margin">Eſt. 5.11, 12, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>Haman</hi> in the midſt of honours met with a <hi>diſgrace</hi> that damped all his joy: ſo he who is moſt happy for the world, either hath, or yer long will meet with one croſſe or other, that may fill his head with <hi>carefull</hi> and diſcontented thoughts. And theſe cares, as they do diſquiet the man, ſo they do offend God, and are therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 6.25. &amp;c. Luk. 12.22. &amp;c. Philip. 4.6.</note> in Scriptures. In reſpect whereof I think it will not be without uſe, to take a view of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of theſe <hi>cares,</hi> and to aſſay, whether ſuch <hi>reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> may be found out, as may ſerue either to <hi>cure</hi> or to <hi>eaſe</hi> them. And for that end, theſe particulars ſeeme in mine opinion, not to be unfit, nor unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>What kinde of Care it is, that is here to be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>What ſignes or markes there be, by which ſinfull Cares may be diſcerned from thoſe that be lawfull and faultleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>What euills or inconueniences ſinfull Cares do breede or produce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>What remedies may be uſed to redreſſe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2456:3"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>What kinde of Care it is whereof here we ſeeke the cure.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very <hi>cure</hi> preſuppoſeth a <hi>malady;</hi> and therfore when we ſeeke a <hi>cure</hi> of <hi>Cares,</hi> it is ſuppoſed to be of ſuch onely as are evill. And yet it cannot bee denyed, but as <hi>careleſſeneſſe</hi> is vitious, ſo ſome <hi>care</hi> may be lawfull and vertuous: and therefore it will bee neceſſary in the entrance, for avoiding of confuſion, to difference them, each from other. And for that purpoſe wee may firſt conſider the uſes of the word, and then the diverſities that are found in the thing; and from either of them ſelect that which may fit the purpoſe in hand.</p>
               <p n="1">I. And firſt for the word, wee may note two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That <hi>Care</hi> in propriety of ſpeech is an apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the minde to think on ſome object, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication we may alſo call a regarding of it. And in this generall acception it anſwereth to the Latine word [<hi>cura,</hi>] and to the Greeke words [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] and [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] or rather to the ſubſtantive noune inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in theſe verbes. As <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.14. the Phariſes and Herodians ſay unto Chriſt, <hi>Maſter, we know that thou art true, and careſt for no man,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] and they give a reaſon of their ſaying ſo, <hi>for thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeſt not the perſon of men;</hi> implying in this ſpeech, that not to <hi>regard</hi> men, is as much as not to <hi>care</hi> for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2456:4"/>them. And ſo is the word uſed
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mar. 4.38. Luke 10.40. Io. 10.13. Act. 18.17. 1 Tim. 3.5. &amp;c.</note> elſewhere often. But yet many times the Engliſh word [<hi>care,</hi>] as alſo the Latine [<hi>cura,</hi>] from whence it is derived, doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and import an <hi>earneſt</hi> and <hi>vehement</hi> intention of the mind; and is the ſame with the Latine [<hi>ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo,</hi>] and the Greek [
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.12. &amp; 2 Cor. 8.16.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Matt. 6.25, 28, 38. Luke 10 41.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:] in which ſenſe our Engliſh Bible doth ſometimes tranſlate theſe words [<hi>earneſt care,</hi>] as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.16. and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times [<hi>carefulneſſe,</hi>] as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.32. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. And in this acception we take the word in this place, that is, for <hi>carefulneſſe,</hi> or an <hi>earneſt care.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 We may note that properly the word [<hi>care</hi>] doth import an applying or bending of the minde about ſome <hi>future</hi> thing, that we may obtaine our intent or deſire in it. For in orderly proceeding, all care or ſtudy of minde is for effecting ſomething, that we do deſire to bring about. And therefore <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, that
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Solicitudo importat ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quoddam adhibitum ad aliquid conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendum. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</hi> 2.2. <hi>q</hi> 5 <hi>s. art.</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Care is a ſtudy applyed to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of ſome thing.</hi> But yet ſometimes through the corruption of men, who not ſeldome do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the right order of things, <hi>care</hi> and ſtudy is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about that which is <hi>paſt,</hi> and things that are <hi>impoſsible,</hi> and ſuch as cannot be ordered or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by us: as when a man bendeth his thoughts, and beateth his braines with muſing and idle thoughts about ſome miſchance or accident, which he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth cannot be amended, nor doth ever fall into the deliberation of a wiſe man. In this place I extend the word to both; our <hi>care</hi> being then the more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, when it is the more diſorderly. And ſo much be noted for the word.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Secondly for the thing ſignified by this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2456:4"/>word, we muſt note three diſtinctions; and out of them ſelect that which may ſerve our turne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 1. There are three ſorts of care anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to three ſorts of objects, to which it may bee applyed. For ſome things are <hi>holy,</hi> or ſuch as God hath commanded; and ſome things are <hi>ſinfull,</hi> or ſuch as God doth condemne; and ſome things are of a middle or <hi>indifferent</hi> nature, neither comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nor forbidden, but may as occaſion doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, either be done or left undone without ſinne. And men may be <hi>carefull</hi> about all theſe things. For good men are carefull to performe good duties. So S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the Corinthians, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.11.</note> 
                  <hi>godly ſorrow wrought carefulneſſe in them:</hi> and of the
<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.32.34.</note> 
                  <hi>unmaried man and woman,</hi> that <hi>they care for the things of the Lord, how they may pleaſe the Lord, and may be holy both in body and in ſpirit.</hi> And of himſelfe he ſaith, that <hi>upon him lay the care of all the Churches.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, wicked men are <hi>carefull</hi> about their evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and deſires. So <hi>Micah</hi> ſaith of them, that
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Micah 7.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>they lye in waite for blood, and that they doe evill with both hands earneſtly:</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, that
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Prov. 4.16.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſleepe not, except they have done miſchiefe; and their ſleepe is taken away, unleſſe they cauſe ſome to fall.</hi> Thirdly, all ſorts of men are <hi>carefull</hi> about the things of this life.
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Luke 10.41</note> 
                  <hi>Martha was carefull and troubled about many things:</hi> all of them belonging to provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the body, and entertainment of friends. And
<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.33.34.</note> he that is <hi>maried, careth for the things of the world, how he may pleaſe his wife:</hi> — and <hi>ſhee that is maried, careth for the things of the world, how ſhe may pleaſe her husband.</hi> The firſt ſort is a <hi>godly</hi> care, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2456:5"/>ſecond is a <hi>deviliſh</hi> care, and the third is a <hi>worldly</hi> care; and that is it whereof now we do enquire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſt.</hi> 2. Secondly, this <hi>worldly care,</hi> or care for the things of this world, is of two ſorts: it is either a <hi>regular</hi> and orderly care, or an <hi>irregular</hi> and exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant care.</p>
               <p>The <hi>regular care</hi> is, when according to the rule of wiſedome and Gods word, we forecaſt and ſtudy how to procure our lawfull ends and deſires. Now the <hi>rules</hi> preſcribed by Gods word for this purpoſe, are three. 1 That the deſire of our ends be moderate. 2 That our purſuit of the meanes conducing to theſe ends, be lawfull. And 3, that there be a patient ſubmiſſion of our deſires and endevours to Gods will and pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That our deſires of worldly bleſſings be <hi>moderate;</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>1</label> ſo that we neither preferre them before more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary things, nor ſpend about them unneceſſary and exceſſive paines. For example, a good man deſireth health, and wealth, and preferments, and honours; but ſo, as that he doth much more deſire grace and Gods fauour, and peace of conſcience, and eternall life. And againe, he beſtoweth paines in ſeeking for the bleſſings of this life, but it is at <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> houres, and without taking up that time, which is due to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things. This I call a <hi>moderate</hi> deſire of our ends: and it is ever neceſſary in ſeeking for worldly things. This rule is preſcribed by our Sauiour, when hee ſaith,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Matt. 6.33.</note> 
                  <hi>Firſt ſeeke the king dome of God and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe:</hi> and was practiſed by the Apoſtle, when
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Philip. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſuffered the loſſe of all things</hi> for Gods cauſe, and <hi>counted them but dung, that he might win Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2456:5"/>
               <p n="2">2 The next <hi>rule</hi> is,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>2</label> that we uſe <hi>lawfull meanes</hi> for attaining of our ends, ſo that wee do not doe any thing for procuring of them, which is contrary to Gods word or will. This <hi>rule</hi> the Apoſtle preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, when for ſeeking of worldly wealth he giveth this direction;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Let him that ſtole, ſteale no more; but rather let him labour, working with his hands the thing that is good, that he may have to give to him that nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</hi> In this paſſage we may note three things for our purpoſe: (1) The <hi>end</hi> that is deſired; and that is, that a man may have ſufficiency, not only to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his owne wants, but to relieve the wants of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo. (2) The <hi>meanes,</hi> that is forbidden to bee uſed for this end; and that is <hi>ſtealing,</hi> and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other unjuſt dealing. And (3) the <hi>meanes</hi> that is commanded; and that is <hi>labour</hi> and paines-taking, by doing ſome worke that is lawfull and good. This is the Apoſtles rule in ſeeking for wealth: and the ſame ſhould be ours in our deſires and cares for all other worldly things.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The laſt <hi>rule</hi> is,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>3</label> that we <hi>ſubmit</hi> our deſires to Gods will, and leave our endevours with patience, to be ordered by his providence. This <hi>rule</hi> was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by our Saviour, when he taught us to pray, <hi>Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heaven.</hi> And himſelfe did practiſe it, when he ſaid,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Matt. 26.39 &amp; Luke 22.42.</note> 
                  <hi>O my Father, if it bee poſsible, let this cup paſſe from me: nevertheleſſe, not as I will, but as thou wilt.</hi> For here he earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red preſervation from death, and yet patiently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelfe to Gods pleaſure, either for life or death. And ſo <hi>David</hi> firſt giveth the rule,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 37.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord: truſt alſo in him, and he ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2456:6"/>bring it to paſſe:</hi> and then followed it in his owne practice,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Sam. 15.25, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſhall finde favour in the eyes of the Lord, he will bring me againe, and ſhew me both it</hi> [the Arke] <hi>and his habitation. But if he thus ſay, I have no delight in thee: behold, here am I, let him doe to me, as ſeemeth good unto him.</hi> And thus the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples at Ceſarea,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Act. 21.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>did beſeech Paul not to goe up to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> where they knew that he was to bee perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted: <hi>but when he would not be perſwaded,</hi> (becauſe he knew it was Gods will to the contrary) <hi>they ceaſed and ſaid, The will of the Lord be done.</hi> And thus muſt we doe: though our deſires bee moſt reaſonable, and our meanes moſt warrantable; yet after all, we muſt <hi>ſubmit</hi> our ſelues to God, and with patience and contentedneſſe referre all to his providence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the granting, or for the denying of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. Now if theſe three rules be obſerved in our ſeeking of worldly things, if our deſires be <hi>moderate,</hi> and our meanes <hi>lawfull,</hi> and all left with due <hi>ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to Gods will and pleaſure; then our care for theſe things is orderly and <hi>regular.</hi> And this care is both allowable and commendable. Firſt, it is <hi>allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> becauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.33, 34.</note> 
                  <hi>He that is maried, careth for the things that are of the world, how he may pleaſe his wife: and ſhe that is maried careth for the things of the world, how ſhe may pleaſe her husband.</hi> For by this ſpeech he meant not to tell us, what maried peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might unjuſtly practice againſt Gods Law, but what they were occaſioned to doe by vertue of their calling. For elſe in all eſtates of life, men and women may deale corruptly, and diſhonour God: and the ſingle life might be ſubject to the like cumbrances,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2456:6"/>that the maried eſtate is. Secondly, I ſay further, that this kinde of care is <hi>commendable,</hi> becauſe it is that meanes, by which God hath appointed us to ſerve his providence. For to truſt to Gods help without uſing our owne care, is not ſo much to <hi>truſt</hi> God, as to <hi>tempt</hi> him. And therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſluggard to the Piſmire, to learne care and providence of her, in that
<note n="(*)" place="margin">Prov. 6.8.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhee provideth her meat in the ſummer, and gathereth her food in the harveſt.</hi> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> telleth us, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>if any man provide not for his owne, and ſpecially for thoſe of his houſe; he hath denied the faith, and is worſe then an infidell.</hi> This care then is a thing both allowed and commended in Scriptures: and therefore is not that <hi>care,</hi> for which we need to preſcribe any <hi>cure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now in the ſecond place there is an <hi>irregular</hi> and exorbitant care: and that is, when contrary to the former <hi>rules</hi> of Gods Law wee ſeeke after our wiſhed ends. 1. If we deſire things of the world too <hi>immoderately</hi> or too eagerly: as if wee preferre them before Gods ſervice, or ſo ſeeke for them, that we neglect good duties, or any way affect them more then according to their worth and value. In this ſort <hi>Eſau</hi> offended, when he
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 12.16. &amp; Gen. 25.31, 32, 33.</note> 
                  <hi>ſold his birthright for one morſell of meate.</hi> Nor was <hi>Rachel</hi> free from this ſinne, when ſhe ſaid,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 30.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Give me children; or elſe I die.</hi> For the one preferred his belly before his right to the bleſſing: and the other deſired children with impatiency againſt God. 2. If wee uſe <hi>evill meanes</hi> for the effecting of our deſires; then is our care <hi>irregular</hi> and unlawfull; becauſe ſinne is no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly or fit way to procure Gods bleſſings by. This
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2456:7"/>was the ſinne of <hi>Saul,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Sam. 28.6, 7.</note> who when God would not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him, went to a witch</hi> for counſell: and the ſinne of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> who in his ſickneſſe,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 King. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſent to Baalze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub, to enquire whether he ſhould recover of his diſeaſe:</hi> and the ſin of all thoſe, that <hi>lye</hi> for advantage, or uſe <hi>ſpels</hi> for recovery of health, or commit any ſin for gaining of this worlds goods. 3. It is <hi>irregular</hi> alſo, if we <hi>diſtruſt</hi> Gods providence for the ſucceſſe of our lawfull endeavors, or if wee do not ſubmit our buſineſſes to Gods pleaſure. Thus the King of Iſrael ſinned, when being diſtreſſed with famine, hee ſaid in his fury,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 King. 6.33</note> 
                  <hi>This evill is of the Lord: what ſhould I waite for the Lord any longer?</hi> And the <hi>Noble</hi> man of the ſame King, when hee diſtruſted Gods word delivered by the Prophet, and ſaid,
<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 King. 7.2.</note> 
                  <hi>If the Lord would make windowes in heaven, might this thing be?</hi> And ſo do all they ſinne, who think (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith the wicked ſay)
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iob 21.15.</note> 
                  <hi>What is the Almighty—? and what profit ſhall wee have, if wee pray unto him?</hi> And they who think, if beſides their labour and paines-taking, they do not uſe <hi>ſhifts</hi> and deceitfull dealing, they may become beggers, for all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Gods bleſſing upon their endeavors. In theſe three reſpects our care may become <hi>irregular.</hi> And in the firſt reſpect it may properly be called an <hi>immoderate</hi> care, becauſe men do exceſſively deſire their ends. In the ſecond, it is properly an <hi>inordinate</hi> care, becauſe thereby men purſue their ends in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly manner. And in the third it is properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>diffident</hi> and <hi>anxious</hi> care, becauſe it is joyned with anxiety of minde, and diſtruſt in Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: But commonly all theſe properties goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2456:7"/>and all of them may be indifferently called by any one of theſe names. For he that deſireth or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for the world <hi>immoderately,</hi> will not ſtick at the meanes, nor truſt God with the ſucceſſe, or with patience expect the event. And if our care for the things of this life, have any of theſe ſinfull condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; then it is an <hi>irregular</hi> and unlawfull care. And that is it which is forbidden by our Saviour, when he ſaith,
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Matt. 6.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Take no thought</hi> (or
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>bee not carefull</hi>) <hi>for your life, what ye ſhall eate, or what ye ſhall drink; nor for your body, what ye ſhall put on:</hi> and by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, when he ſaith,
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Philip. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Be carefull for nothing.</hi> And it is the care that is here propounded, and is to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 3. This <hi>irregular</hi> care for things of the world, may be of two ſorts. 1 If we do <hi>diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly</hi> deſire to <hi>obtaine</hi> ſome worldly good. As for example, the <hi>covetous</hi> man, when he hath too much already, yet wearieth and weareth himſelfe with ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for more; and the <hi>Ambitious</hi> man, when he hath greater places of honour, then hee can manage or diſcharge, yet ſtriveth to come higher ſtill: yea and the <hi>poore</hi> man doth ſometimes too eagerly and too immoderately deſire a competent meanes of living in the world. And all of them do unlawfully care and ſeeke for a worldly good. 2 This <hi>irregular</hi> care may be, by ſeeking to <hi>avoid</hi> ſome worldly evill. As namely thoſe that be in <hi>priſon,</hi> may take too much care, how they may be freed: and thoſe that bee in <hi>want,</hi> how they may be relieved: and thoſe that bee <hi>ſick,</hi> how they may bee recovered. In the former kinde <hi>Rachel</hi> ſinned, when ſhee did immoderately
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2456:8"/>deſire to beare children: and in the later kinde <hi>Eſau</hi> ſinned, when he did exceſſively deſire the ſatisfying of his hunger. And both of theſe are within the compaſſe of the ſubject, here to be ſpoken of. The concluſion then is, All <hi>care</hi> for things of this life, whether it be for <hi>obtaining</hi> of ſome good, or for <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyding</hi> of any evill, if it be <hi>irregular</hi> in ſuch ſort as hath beene formerly deſcribed; is that which the Scriptutes condemne under the name of <hi>worldly cares,</hi> and is the thing to be enquired into in this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>What ſignes or tokens there bee, to diſcerne this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full care by.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto we have conſidered the nature of <hi>worldly cares,</hi> as they are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Scriptures, and have thereby differenced them in good part from ſuch cares as are lawfull and allowed by Gods word: but yet becauſe men are willing to flatter themſelves in thoſe things which they delight in, and will thereupon be apt to deceive themſelves, in judging their care of the world to bee a <hi>moderate</hi> providing for their eſtate, when it is indeed an <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> and exceſſive carking for the world: it will be neceſſary in the next place, to ſet downe ſome fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible markes and ſignes, whereby ſinfull cares may be more eaſily diſcovered and diſcerned to be ſuch.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2456:8"/>And for that purpoſe wee may take notice of theſe tokens following.</p>
               <p n="1">I. If cares do fill the head and heart of a man at <hi>unſeaſonable</hi> times; that is a ſigne, that they are <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate</hi> and exceſſive. For the <hi>moderate</hi> and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent care maketh a man <hi>diligent</hi> about his worke, when <hi>opportunitie</hi> ſerveth for his benefite and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: but if a man take care, when the time ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not, and then bee thinking on the world, when hee ſhould bee buſied about other matters, that is too much care, and exceedeth due proportion and meaſure. And ſuch are the cares of thoſe men, who <hi>minde earthly things.</hi> For they fill the head with thoughts, and the heart with feares, even then, when a man intends other occaſions, and both ſhould and would bee thinking on better things. If he goe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way, and leave them (as he thinketh) behinde him, they will attend him ſtill: they will follow him to his <hi>bed,</hi> and to his <hi>board,</hi> and to his <hi>cloſet.</hi> They are at his heeles, or rather in his head, when he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the fields for his recreation; and when he is diſpoſing of his houſhold for their imployments, and when hee is in the Church about his devotions, and when he goeth to bed to reſt and refreſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and if hee be in bed, yet he ſleepeth not; if hee be in the Church, hee prayeth not; and if hee heare a Sermon, hee underſtandeth not what is ſaid. And all this, becauſe the minde being full of thoughts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, hath no roome for other things to enter in. And this, all men will ſay is too much and without reaſon: and therefore if wee obſerve our ſelves, and finde our cares thus poſſeſſing our heads, wee may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2456:9"/>reſolve, theſe be very <hi>irregular</hi> and unlawfull cares. This is the firſt ſigne.</p>
               <p n="2">II. A ſecond is, Theſe cares may be knowne to bee <hi>irregular,</hi> if they buſie and take up a mans thoughts about ſuch things, as are not in his power to order or diſpoſe or alter any way for his aduantage. For the <hi>regular</hi> care maketh a man <hi>diligent</hi> to uſe good meanes for his honeſt ends, and when once he hath done what is in his owne power, and belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to his dutie to doe, hee leaveth caring for that which hee cannot compaſſe. But exceſſive and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate</hi> care doth not only buſie men about the meanes, which themſelues may vſe, but about the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and ſucceſſe of their labours, which is in Gods hand only, either to grant or to denie. When they have done all that they can doe, yet they reſt not there; but they feare and doubt, and forecaſt dangers and difficulties, and muſe with themſelues what the event may bee; and if any thing fall out amiſſe, they <hi>take thought</hi> for that which is alreadie paſt, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be recalled: as if the Husbandman, when hee hath plowed and ſowed and weeded, and done all that belongeth to the art of tillage, ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward beate his braines, and buſie his minde with thinking, how the corne will grow, and how the weather will prove, and what a croppe he may have at the harveſt. And this is evident to bee <hi>fooliſh</hi> and ſuperfluous: and therefore if wee finde thoughts of of things without our compaſſe, we may know that to be an <hi>irregular</hi> and unlawfull care.</p>
               <p n="3">III. A third ſigne of a ſinfull care, is; if it vexe the minde and diſquiet the man, and bereave him of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2456:9"/>his inward peace and contentment. For the orderly care, maketh a man to <hi>adviſe,</hi> and provide, &amp; labour for that which may availe him; and when hee hath once done working, then hee leaveth caring, glad that his worke is at an end; Yea, and he comforteth himſelfe with the conſcience of his well doing: and becauſe he hath done his owne endeavours, hee <hi>lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> himſelfe <hi>downe in peace,</hi> and with patience expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth Gods bleſſing according to his promiſe. But <hi>anxious</hi> and diſtruſtfull cares, they worke vpon the man, when they cannot worke about the thing: they do not onely fill the head with thoughts, but the heart with heavineſs; and breed ſorow, when they cannot further the ſucceſſe. For which cauſe the Greekes call this care [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] becauſe it doth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> cut and divide the minde in peeces. And the Latines call it <hi>[cura,]</hi> becauſe it doth <hi>cor edere,</hi> feede upon and conſume the heart. And in the Hebrew tongue the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſame word ſignifieth both to take thought or to be <hi>carefull,</hi> and to ſorow or bee <hi>grieved:</hi> and our Engliſh Bibles do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times render it the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Sam. 9.5</note> one way, and ſometimes the other
<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pſal. 38.18.</note>; the unitie of the word implying a neare affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in the things. And wee in our Engliſh tongue when wee ſee a man pine and waſte and weare away without apparent cauſe, we ſay, <hi>He taketh eare,</hi> or <hi>Hee taketh thought</hi> for ſome thing; meaning that his cares breede <hi>ſorow,</hi> and his ſorow <hi>ſicknes.</hi> And this muſt needes be a great deale too much, when that which ſhould help to ſpeede our buſineſſe, doth ſerve to conſume our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. A fourth ſigne may bee this: If our care
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2456:10"/>for earthly things do breede <hi>feares</hi> and <hi>ſuſpitions</hi> without cauſe, that is a ſigne that it doth affect us o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much and aboue meaſure. For <hi>ordinate</hi> care as it <hi>uſeth helps</hi> to effect his ends, ſo it <hi>provideth</hi> againſt lets and dangers that might hinder them; but both of them with moderation, and as reaſon doth require. But if a mans heart be ſet on the world, his loue to earthly things, and the care that hee hath of them, doth make him feare every ſhadow, and ſuſpect e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very fancy; much what like a skittiſh jade, that ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at every ſtraw. And as <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid out of his diſcontent and diffidence,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 4.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Every one that findeth me, ſhall ſlay mee;</hi> when as there was never a one in the world, but his owne father and mother: ſo theſe men doubt leſt every great man that they meete with, will oppreſſe them; and every poore man will ſteale from them; and every paſſenger, will robbe them; and every chapman or cuſtomer, wil overreach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; every man that they deale with will one way or other deprive them of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities &amp; riches: nor dare they truſt any man fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they ſee him. For according as any mans <hi>love</hi> is to the world, ſo will his <hi>feares</hi> be, leſt hee loſe that which hee loveth.</p>
               <p>Theſe bee the <hi>ſignes</hi> and <hi>ſymptomes</hi> of an <hi>anxious, diffident, inordinate</hi> and <hi>immoderate</hi> care. If any man feele them in himſelfe or finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in others, he may bee ſure that ſuch men are diſtempered with this ſicknes of worldly <hi>cares:</hi> and therefore have neede to ſeeke for, and to make uſe of whatſoever <hi>cure,</hi> may bee preſcribed for their better eaſe and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2456:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>What evils accompany this irregular care.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ares, ſuch as have beene already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, have many ill conſequents and companions; which may iuſtly move us with all care to remove them, and to ridde our ſelves of them. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">I They <hi>buſie</hi> and <hi>vexe</hi> men with exceſſive toile, and yet they no way help him, or make him any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for his paines. And this appeareth by two things: 1 becauſe they are <hi>needleſſe</hi> and without uſe: and 2, becauſe they are <hi>fruitleſſe</hi> and without effect.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they are <hi>needleſſe</hi> and without uſe. For if men would doe their parts, God will bee ſure to doe his: that is, if they uſe honeſt meanes, as hee hath appointed; he will procure a happy iſſue, as himſelfe hath promiſed: This the Apoſtle teacheth us,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Caſt all your care upon God; for he careth for you.</hi> And Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 37.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord, and truſt in him; and he will bring it to paſſe.</hi> And our Saviour,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 6.33</note> 
                  <hi>Seeke ye firſt the kingdome of God and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and all theſe things</hi> [of the world] <hi>ſhall be added unto you.</hi> And if God do take care of us, and will bring to paſſe our deſires, and caſt upon us all neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things, when we have done our dutie, and do reſt upon his providence: what a <hi>vanity,</hi> nay ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is it, to beate our braines about thoſe things, which, if wee would leave them to Gods diſpoſing, would without our care bee better done to our hands?</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2456:11"/>
               <p>Secondly, they are <hi>fruitleſſe</hi> and without effect, and do no way help forward or further the thing which wee care or labour for. For
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Matt. 6.27. Luk. 12.25.</note> 
                  <hi>which of you</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>by taking thought can adde one cubite to his ſtature?</hi> His meaning is, that no <hi>thought,</hi> nor care, nor anxietie of minde, can effect our deſires, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the ſucceſſe; which is only in Gods power to give. And ſo, in like ſort, we may reaſon of all other the like caſes: Which of vs by ſitting in a corner, (though wee ſhould weepe our bellies full) can by this carking care, either cure a diſeaſe in our bodies, or make up a breach in our eſtates, or pacifie the broiles in our houſe, or bring to life againe a decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed friend? No. Theſe bee things, which if God do not give them, we cannot have them. Thus this care, and vexation of ſpirit, is both <hi>needleſſe</hi> without uſe, and <hi>fruitleſſe</hi> without effect: and in both reſpects wee may ſay that this <hi>irregular</hi> care doth cumber us and not help us.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Immoderate</hi> cares do make our life to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>comfort.</hi> For God
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 104.15.</note> hath given us both <hi>bread to ſtrengthen</hi> us, <hi>and wine to make the heart glad, and oile to make the face ſhine;</hi> as David ſpeaketh: and hee it is that
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Act. 14.17.</note> 
                  <hi>filleth our hearts with foode and gladnes.</hi> The meaning of which ſayings is, that God doth not only beſtow on us <hi>neceſſarie</hi> things that may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve life, but <hi>comfortable</hi> things alſo, that may make it joyfull; and would not only have his ſervants to live, but while they live, to rejoyce alſo. But cares take away this joy: they are ever accompanied with ſadnes and ſorow; and
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Prov. 15.13. and 12.25.</note> 
                  <hi>by ſorow in the heart</hi> (ſaith Salomon) <hi>the ſpirit is broken,</hi> &amp; <hi>a
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Prov. 17.22.</note> broken ſpirit drieth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2456:11"/>the bones:</hi> ſo that all the dayes of the afflicted [ſpirit] <hi>are evill; but a mery heart is a continuall feaſt.</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect whereof we may ſay of ſuch a man, that he <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth</hi> not life, while he <hi>poſſeſſeth</hi> it: and that his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſoule doth but ſerve to make his paines ſenſible. Nay, ſorow doth not only deprive mans life of the <hi>comfort</hi> which God hath given him; but doth even deprive the man of life it ſelfe. For to ſay nothing of thoſe, who being oppreſſed with cares, do with their owne hands haſten their death; this <hi>ſadneſſe</hi> in the ſoule, doth by degrees ſhorten our time, and that when we think not on it.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Sam. 1.7, 8</note> It made <hi>Hannah</hi> to <hi>weepe,</hi> and to forgoe her foode.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Kings 21.4, 5.</note> It made <hi>Ahab</hi> ſick, &amp; betake himſelfe to his bed. And (as the Apoſtle ſaith) in the end,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>it worketh death.</hi> And thus cares do make the life <hi>uncomfortable,</hi> and without joy.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Immoderate</hi> cares do make men <hi>unfit</hi> for Gods <hi>ſervice:</hi> and that in two reſpects. 1 Becauſe he that is dejected with griefe, cannot bee cheerefull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any worke: much leſſe, can hee that is grieved with worldly cares, be free hearted to ſo contrary a work, as is Gods ſervice. But as
<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Kin. 3.15</note> 
                  <hi>Eliſhah</hi> was then fit to prophecie, when <hi>the minſtrell played</hi> before him: ſo men are then fit to heare and reade and pray with devotion and zeale, when their hearts are enlarged with joy and gladnes. And therefore God requireth,
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Deut. 28.47</note> that when men <hi>have abundance of all things, they ſhould ſerve the Lord with joyfulnes and gladnes of heart.</hi> 2, Cares make us <hi>unfit</hi> to ſerve God, becauſe the heart being taken up with earthly thoughts, hath no leiſure to attend to heavenly things. But as hee that is in a deepe ſtudie, or is muſing on ſome matter
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2456:12"/>with intention of minde, ſeeth not the things that are before his eyes, or if hee ſee them, yet noteth them not: ſo hee whoſe minde is filled with cares of the world, heareth not what the Preacher ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, or if he heareth it, he obſerveth it not: nay, when himſelfe praieth, his heart knoweth not what his mouth ſpeaketh. And no marvell: for the heart is away all the while, ranging here and there, where his thoughts bee. Or if ſuch a man faſten upon any thing in the publike miniſterie; Yet his care of the world carieth him from the Church to other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; and they do ſo wholly take up his thoughts, that bee thinketh no more on that which hee had once heard: &amp; ſo the ſeede that was ſowen, for want of watering it by meditation, never groweth up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practiſe. For which cauſe our Saviour telleth us, that
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Matt. 13.22</note> 
                  <hi>the care of this world doth choke the word;</hi> and warneth us to
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Luk. 21.34.</note> 
                  <hi>take heede, leſt our hearts be overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with ſurfetting and drunkennes and cares of this life: and ſo that day</hi> [of the Lord] <hi>come upon us at una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares.</hi> In which admonition we may conſider theſe particulars. (1) What he warneth us of, and it is <hi>ſurfetting</hi> and <hi>drunkennes</hi> and <hi>cares of this life:</hi> hee joyneth theſe three together, becauſe though they differ in nature, yet they agree in one worke or effect. (2) What the effect is, which they cauſe, <hi>they overcharge the heart,</hi> that is, they preſſe it downe to the ground with the heavie burden that they lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. <hi>Surfetting</hi> burdeneth it with exceſſe of meate; <hi>drunkennes</hi> with abundance of drinke; and <hi>worldly cares</hi> with anxious and diſtracting thoughts: and all of them keepe it downe, and make it lie grove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2456:12"/>upon the ground. (3) What the danger hereof is; and that is, men are unprepared and unready for the comming of Chriſt unto judgement, ſo that <hi>that day commeth upon them at unawares:</hi> and hee that is not prepared to give his account, will never bee able to abide the laſt ſentence. Thus cares make men <hi>unfit</hi> for Gods ſervice, and conſequently for their laſt reckoning.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. <hi>Immoderate</hi> and diſtruſtfull cares, as they deprive our ſelves of comfort, ſo they <hi>rob</hi> God of his <hi>honour.</hi> For if we will deale juſtly with God, and devide aright betweene him and our ſelves, in the managing and ordering of all our affaires and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ours is the <hi>labour,</hi> his is the <hi>ſucceſſe:</hi> to us it belongeth to uſe lawfull meanes, but to him to give a bleſſing, and to proſper the meanes, that wee have uſed. This the Pſalmiſt teacheth us,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it:</hi> and, <hi>except the Lord keepe the City, the watchman waketh but in vaine.</hi> And, <hi>it is vaine for you to riſe up early, to ſit up late, and to eate the bread of ſorowes.</hi> And ſo the Apoſtle,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>planted, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos watered, but God gave the increaſe.</hi> And our Saviour ſaith of the husbandman, that
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mar. 4.26.</note> 
                  <hi>hee caſteth ſeede into the ground, and ſleepeth, and riſeth night and day, and the ſeede ſpringeth and groweth up, hee knoweth not how.</hi> And,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.37, 38.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſoweſt not that body which ſhall be, but bare graine, it may chance of wheat or of ſome other ſeede: but God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it a body, as it hath pleaſed him; and to every ſeede his owne body.</hi> By which ſayings we may ſee that the <hi>husbandman</hi> after his daies labor may take his nights
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2456:13"/>reſt, and never trouble himſelfe about the ſpringing of the ſeede; becauſe that is a thing, that is out of his reach, and it is God alone that doth make the corne grow without his thinking on it. But againe, ſuppoſe the <hi>husbandman</hi> ſhould bee ſo fooliſh, as when he hath done ſeeding, to watch all night, and to toſſe up and downe upon his bed, and beate his braines in pieces with thinking on the growth of his corne, and caring for a plentifull harveſt; yet for all this, neither would his corne grow the better, nor his barnes at the harveſt prove ever a whit the fuller. And thus it is in all other caſes and buſineſſes of the world: The <hi>labour</hi> is ours, and our part it is to uſe the meanes; but the <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> is Gods, and his part it is either to withhold, or to beſtow a bleſſing. And therefore, if any man take upon him to forecaſt and provide for the ſucceſſe and event of things, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by uſing fit meanes for it; (as the carefull and anxious man doth; who ſtill continueth his care after he hath done his worke:) he doth hereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach upon Gods right, and rob him of one part of his <hi>glory,</hi> which he will not impart to any other.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>Immoderate</hi> and <hi>diſtruſtfull</hi> cares will bee a meanes to hinder our deſired ends, and will even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of that ſucceſſe for which wee take all the care. For if with <hi>patience</hi> and ſubmiſſion wee could leave things to be ordered by Gods providence, hee would not faile to effect our deſires: but if we <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt</hi> Gods providence, and dare not relye on his word; it will bee juſt with God to leave us to our ſelves, and to deny us his preſence and protection: as
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 King. 7.2.</note> 
                  <hi>the Prince,</hi> that would not beleeve Gods word
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2456:13"/>ſpoken by the Prophet, was made to ſee the truth of it, but was denied to enjoy the fruit of it. This point, at leaſt for the former branch of it, hath beene in part confirmed already; and may in both the branches of it, bee further declared by two contrary examples: the one in <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Patriarch <hi>Abraham. Peter</hi> doubted of Chriſts word, and thereby loſt his protection: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> beleeved in hope againſt hope, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with a bleſſing. But to declare theſe inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more fully:</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Peter</hi> we reade thus,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Matth 4.28. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, if it bee thou, bid me come unto thee on the water. And he ſaid, Come. And when Peter was come downe out of the ſhip, he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on the water to goe to Ieſus. But when hee ſaw the winde boiſterous, he was afraid; and beginning to ſink, he cryed ſaying, Lord ſave me. And immediately Ieſus ſtretched forth his hand and caught him, and ſaid unto him, O thou of little faith, wherefore didſt thou doubt?</hi> In this example there are theſe things conſiderable: 1, We may note <hi>Peters confidence</hi> and ſtedfaſt faith: he offered and adventured on his Maſters word, to walke upon the Sea, without any other prop to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him. 2, His <hi>doubting</hi> and diffidence. When he ſaw <hi>the winde boiſterous,</hi> and the ſea ſwelling, and the billowes ready to overwhelme him, then hee was afraid of the danger, and doubted leſt notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Chriſts promiſe, he might periſh in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. 3, The <hi>event</hi> and ſucceſſe of all. And that is, <hi>Peter</hi> never began to <hi>ſink,</hi> till he began to <hi>doubt:</hi> hee walked upon the waters as ſafely, as a man may walk in a pathway. But when once he diſtruſted, then he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2456:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2456:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2456:15"/>ſank downewards: and but that Gods mercy was the greater, and Chriſt <hi>caught</hi> him by the hand, hee might have beene drowned in the depth. And ſo it is with us; If we dare truſt God upon his word, we ſhall be ſafe in the greateſt danger, though wee were in the midſt of the ſea, without any other ſtay, but the hand of Gods providence to uphold us. But if we let goe our hold upon Gods word, and dare not relye upon his promiſe; it is no marvell, if we ſink, like leade, and periſh in the waters. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell then it is, that we do ſo often faint, and faile, and fall downe under the burden. For which of us would not doe as S. <hi>Peter</hi> did; feare to be drowned, if wee were in the midſt of the ſea, and ſhaken with a boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous winde? Nay, which of us durſt doe as hee did; adventure to go upon the ſea, when God ſhould command it? Surely God hath bidden us deale juſtly, and to
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> 
                  <hi>have our converſation without cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe:</hi> and hath promiſed, that he <hi>will never leave nor forſake us.</hi> But we notwithſtanding feare, and ſay, that <hi>if we doe not as others doe,</hi> that is, ſhift and lye, and put off baſe wares, and over-reach in our bargaining, we may <hi>goe a begging, and ſhut up our ſhop windowes.</hi> Againe, God hath commanded us, that if men oppoſe us, while wee are about his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, wee ſhould not
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ier. 1.17. Ezek. 2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>be diſmayed at their faces, nor afraid of their words:</hi> and he hath promiſed that in ſuch a caſe he will
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ier. 1.18, 19. Ezek. 3.8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>make us a defenced city, and an iron pillar, and walls of braſſe againſt Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Prieſts and People:</hi> and <hi>though they fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, yet they ſhall not prevaile againſt us.</hi> But we, if a Great man require of us that which is unjuſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2456:15"/>to be done, and ſhew us an angry face for doing of our dutie; wee tremble at the ſight, and our hearts quake within us,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſ. 7.2.</note> 
                  <hi>as the trees of the wood are ſhaken with the winde.</hi> And againe to take an inſtance, which is more direct to the point in hand: God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Philip. 4.6, 7</note> 
                  <hi>Be carefull for nothing: but in every thing by prayer and ſupplication with thankſgiving, let your requeſts be made knowne unto God.</hi> And he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that if we obey, then <hi>the peace of God, which paſſeth all underſtanding, ſhall keepe our hearts and minds through Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> And againe hee hath commanded,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 37.5, 7, 9</note> 
                  <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord, and reſt on the Lord, and waite patiently for him:</hi> and he hath promiſed that he <hi>will bring to paſſe</hi> our deſires, and that they <hi>who waite upon the Lord ſhall inherite the earth.</hi> But wee, if wee meete with a croſſe, ſicknes in our bodies, weaknes in our eſtates, diſgraces on our perſons, or any other misfortune or diſtreſſe; wee runne to a corner, and weep till our eyes bee wearie, and make our owne hearts ſad with muſing on our miſerie, and forecaſting dangers of undoing.</p>
               <p>Now while wee thus <hi>diſtruſt</hi> Gods word, we have no warrant to expect his help: but if we <hi>feare</hi> with <hi>Peter,</hi> we muſt looke to <hi>ſinke</hi> with him. And this ſheweth that diſtruſtfull cares prevent us of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
               <p>The other <hi>example</hi> is in <hi>Abraham</hi> the <hi>father of the faithfull.</hi> Of him it is ſtoried, that
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Gen. 22.1, 2 &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>God tried him, &amp; ſaid, Take now thy ſon, thine only ſon Iſaac, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou loveſt, and get thee into the land of Moriah: &amp; offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the mountaines, that I will tell thee off. And Abraham roſe up early in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2456:16"/>the morning &amp;c. Then on the third day Abraham lift up his eyes, and ſaw the place afarre off: &amp;c. And A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham tooke the wood of the burnt offering, and laied it upon Iſaac his ſonne; and he tooke the fire in his hand, and a knife, and they went both of them together &amp;c. And they came to the place:—and Abraham built an Altar there, and laied the wood in order, and bound Iſaac his ſonne, and laied him on the Altar upon the wood. And Abraham ſtretched forth his hand, and tooke the knife to ſlaie his ſonne. And the Angel of the Lord called unto him out of heaven,—&amp; ſaid, Lay not thine hand upon the Lad, neither doe any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: for now I know that thou feareſt God, ſeeing thou haſt not withheld thy ſonne, thine only ſonne from mee.</hi> In this <hi>example</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> wee may note theſe particulars, and make uſe of them for our direction. (1) What <hi>Abraham</hi> was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to doe: and it was that hee ſhould <hi>take his only ſonne,</hi> the ſtaffe of his age, the hope of his poſteritie, the joy of his life, and (which is moſt of all) the ground of Gods promiſes towards him in Chriſt. For God had promiſed that in <hi>Abraham and his ſeede all the nations of the earth ſhould bee bleſſed:</hi> and that ſeede he had appointed <hi>Iſaac</hi> to bee. For
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 21.12</note> 
                  <hi>In Iſaac</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>ſhall thy ſeed be called.</hi> Beſides, this ſonne, whom <hi>Abraham</hi> loved, and that deſervedly for many reſpects, hee was commanded to carie three dayes journey off, and to kill him with his owne hands, and to offer him up in a burnt ſacrifice unto God. An hard taske, and a grievous ſtorme, by which <hi>Abraham</hi> was put to the triall, what hee would doe for God. (2) Note, what <hi>Abraham</hi> in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2456:16"/>this caſe performed, and that was even all that was required of him. Hee <hi>tooke his ſonne,</hi> and caried the <hi>wood</hi> and the <hi>knife,</hi> and went three dayes journey, &amp; <hi>bound</hi> the childe, &amp; drew out the knife, and fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the blow, that ſhould have bereaved both <hi>Iſaac</hi> of his life, &amp; <hi>Abraham</hi> of his deareſt ſon. A ſtrong <hi>faith,</hi> and an undainted affiance in God, by which <hi>Abraham</hi> hath ſet us an example, which moſt would rather <hi>commend,</hi> then <hi>imitate.</hi> For one of us, had wee beene in his place, would have thought thus; Lord, why ſhould God deale thus ſtrangely with mee? <q>Was ever man brought to theſe ſtraights, that I am in? and, Is it poſſible, my heart ſhould beare all this, and not breake? Or thus; Can God love mee, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieth mee mine only childe? Will God provide mee comfort, when he taketh from mee all the joy that I have? and, Meaneth hee to performe his promiſe made in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> when hee deſigneth <hi>Iſaac</hi> to be ſlaine, and his bodie to be burnt into aſhes? Or thus; Will nothing pleaſe God, but mine only ſonne? and, Is it not enough, that I part with my ſonne, but I muſt murther him with mine owne hands? and, May I not now at once, make an end both of his life and my griefe; but muſt I be acting it three daies together, that by prolonging the time, I may encreaſe my ſorow?</q> Thus or in ſome ſuch manner, as this wee would have beene ready to have complained againſt God: Or if wee had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt our minds, yet wee would have wept and mourned and wrung the hands, like
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Matt. 2.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Rachel, that wept for her children, and would not bee comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe they were not.</hi> But <hi>Abraham</hi> did neither
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2456:17"/>ſo, nor ſo. He did what God commanded, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for that which God had promiſed; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith of him,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 4.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Againſt hope he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in hope:</hi> and
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 11.17.</note> 
                  <hi>He that had received the promiſes, offered up his only begotten ſonne, of whom it was ſaid, In Iſaac ſhall thy ſeed bee called: accounting that God was able even to raiſe him up from the dead.</hi> And this was that which <hi>Abraham</hi> performed in the time of his tryall. (3) Conſider wee how <hi>Abraham</hi> ſped after all: and that was, an <hi>Angel</hi> ſtaied his hand from killing his ſonne, and God commended his faith, that was ſo readie to obey, &amp; now all ages ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>Abraham</hi> for <hi>the father of the faithfull.</hi> Nor is there any of us, but will thinke and ſay; <q>O happie man that had ſuch a ſonne to give, and ſuch an heart to part with him at Gods command, and ſuch a faith to depend upon God when all things ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med contrarie, and ſuch a bleſſing from God, when he was deſtitute of all help and hope!</q> But this is the end of thoſe, that dare truſt God in their trialls, and with cheerfulneſſe can follow him through their troubles. Let us then <hi>imitate Abrahams</hi> faith, and wee ſhall partake alſo of his <hi>bleſsing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2456:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>What rules or directions wee may follow to eaſe our ſelves of theſe cares.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He evils being ſuch and ſo great which attend <hi>irregular</hi> cares: I ſuppoſe every man will earneſtly deſire ſome <hi>remedies,</hi> that may either <hi>eure</hi> or <hi>abate</hi> them. And no doubt but many would doe their endeavor to be eaſed, if they knew which way to goe about it. And therefore it will bee a ſeaſonable and welcome ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, I ſuppoſe, if in the laſt place we can finde ſome <hi>Rules</hi> that may <hi>direct</hi> us in this worke. And for that purpoſe I have thought on theſe following directions.</p>
               <p n="1">I. When ſuch thoughts do ariſe in our mindes,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>1</label> we muſt not yeeld to them, and give way to our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: much leſſe may we (as men uſe in ſuch caſes to doe) get our ſelves into a ſolitary roome, where we may weepe without being ſeene, and may feede our paſſions with muſing on our miſery, and with framing reaſons that may aggravate our griefe. For all things grow ſtrong, when they are cheriſhed; but theſe naturall diſtempers which ſpring and ſprout ſo eaſily of themſelves, will ſoone become headſtrong, if they be not withſtood, and either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied entrance, or quickly turned out of doores, that they do not ſettle within us. And for that purpoſe we may doe foure things. (1) We muſt <hi>divert</hi> our thoughts ſome other way, and turne them on ſome
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2456:18"/>better object. For as <hi>husbandmen,</hi> when their ground is overflowed with much water, make ditches and water-furrowes to carie it away: ſo if our mindes be over-flowed with cares of the world; there is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way to draine them, then by making another paſſage for them, and by diverting them upon ſome other matter, fitter to be thought upon; eſpecially if we ſet them on worke about ſome ſuch things as may either affect our mindes with ſome uſefull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, or may tend to the mitigating or abating of theſe cares. For which purpoſe, wee may teach our hearts to meditate on the vanity of worldly things; or on the comforts and peace of a good conſcience, or on the ſhortneſſe of this life, or whatſoever other good matter that we can moſt willingly receive and entertaine. For ſuch will finde the eaſieſt entrance, and are likely to abide the longeſt with us. And if our former thoughts and cares do interrupt us, and intermingle themſelves againſt our wills, and ſo breake off, or hinder our meditations: yet we muſt then force our ſelves to call home our wandring thoughts, and labour to drive out theſe fanſies, as
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 15.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham drove away</hi> the birds that lighted on his ſacrifice. (2) We may for the ſame purpoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our ſelves to good <hi>company,</hi> ſuch as whoſe words may <hi>miniſter grace</hi> to our hearts when wee heare them; and whoſe ſavoury talke may poſſeſſe our mindes with a love and liking of them. For look how much we give our mindes to marke ſuch mens diſcourſes, and ſo much wee pare away or diminiſh of our diſtracting thoughts. (3) Wee may, and it will be moſt availeable, if wee do bend and ſet our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2456:18"/>ſelves about the reading of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or peruſing of ſome other wiſe and ſober writings, which may both take up our thoughts, and informe our mindes. So it ſeemeth <hi>David</hi> did in the times of his diſtreſs,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.23</note> 
                  <hi>Princes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>did ſit and ſpeake againſt me: but thy ſervant did meditate in thy ſtatutes.</hi> And againe,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.92</note> 
                  <hi>Vnleſſe thy Law had beene my delight, I ſhould then have periſhed in mine affliction.</hi> By which ſpeeches we may gather, that <hi>David</hi> did not ſit downe and bemone himſelfe with diſcontented thoughts, but hee ranne to Gods <hi>word,</hi> and did meditate in his law, and had comfort from thence in all his troubles. And ſo ſhould wee doe; if any feares afflict our mindes, we ſhould goe to the Booke of God, and buſie our ſelves with thinking on the ſweet ſayings that bee there delivered and taught. (4) Wee ſhould ſet our ſelves with as much chearfulneſſe, as we may, about the <hi>buſineſſes</hi> and works of our <hi>honeſt callings.</hi> For theſe are duties that God requireth at our hands, and they bee employments that wee are well acquainted with, and ſuch buſineſſes withall, as new occaſions every day will put us upon: and in theſe reſpects it will bee the more eaſie to buſie our mindes about the ordering of them. And if theſe have their due place, carefull thoughts will have the leſſe roome. Theſe are the <hi>diverſions</hi> which we may uſe in this caſe: and if thus, or, in any other the like kinde, we ſet our heads and hearts on working; wee ſhall both buſie our mindes with good thoughts that may profit us, and keepe out worldly cares that would annoy us. But if when cares and feares do ſeize upon us, we avoyd <hi>action,</hi> and ſhunne <hi>company,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2456:19"/>and caſt off the care of our <hi>callings,</hi> and get into a <hi>corner,</hi> that wee may give ſcope to our cares, and may invent arguments to amplifie our miſery; it is no martiell, if our feares and cares, and unquiet thoughts get head againſt us, when as our ſelves do uphold them with our owne hands.</p>
               <p n="2">II.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>2</label> We muſt ſtrive to take away the <hi>cauſe,</hi> that breedeth theſe unquiet cares. For as in healing <hi>ſick bodies, Phyſicians</hi> never think the cure to bee ſound, till the cauſe of the diſeaſe bee removed: ſo it is in healing <hi>ſick</hi> and diſtempered <hi>mindes;</hi> there can bee no ſound cure, till the cauſe, which firſt bred the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and afterward doth uphold it, be removed or taken away. Now the cauſes of this ſickneſſe, which in this place we endeavor to cure, are eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally theſe two; An <hi>immoderate love</hi> of worldly things; and a <hi>fearfull diſtruſt</hi> of Gods providence and fatherly care over us.</p>
               <p n="1">1 An <hi>immoderate love</hi> of the world is a cauſe of <hi>inordinate</hi> cares; becauſe
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Matt. 6.21.</note> 
                  <hi>where our treaſure is, there will our hearts alſo be,</hi> as our Saviour ſaith. If our <hi>treaſure,</hi> that is, that which wee eſteeme, and deſire, and love, as ſome ſpeciall jewell of great worth, if it be in heaven; then our hearts will bee in heaven, ever thinking upon, and ever longing after the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall joyes, and the ſociety of the glorious Saints and Angels, and the preſence of the bleſſed Trinity; in the enjoying whereof is <hi>fulneſſe of joy for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> And if our treaſure be upon earth, if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and love the things of this life, as our greateſt good; then our hearts will be upon the earth, ſtill thinking on the world, and ever reaching and gaping
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2456:19"/>after it. Wee ſhall ſometimes bee ſtudying how to <hi>get</hi> them, and ſometimes how to <hi>increaſe</hi> them, and ſometimes how to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of them; and when wee have nothing to doe about them, yet our hearts will delight to looke upon them, and to handle them, as the worldling often telleth over his gold and ſilver; not becauſe hee knoweth not the ſumme, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he delighteth in the ſight and ſound of it. And if once theſe things bee loſt, which are ſo much lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; the heart followeth after them <hi>mourning</hi> and ſorowing that his joy is gone, as when <hi>David</hi> tooke <hi>Michal</hi> away from <hi>Phaltiel</hi> her ſuppoſed husband,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>he went with her along weeping.</hi> For that which a man doth <hi>love</hi> immoderately when hee hath it; for that hee will <hi>mourne</hi> immoderately, when hee hath loſt it. And hence it is, that becauſe <hi>Rachel</hi> did too exceſſively deſire childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, before ſhe had them; therefore the
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ier. 31.15.</note> Prophet doth bring her in, as a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of them that mourne for their children, when they are not. For as it fareth with things that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the bodie, thoſe that are looſe from the fleſh, as our clothes and armour are, theſe wee can put on and off without annoyance or paine; but that which ſticketh to our fleſh, as the skinne doth, if that be pulled or plucked from us, it putteth us to paine, and breedeth ſmart and ſorow: ſo it is with the things of this world, if they be unto us as our clothes, things without us, &amp; ſuch as we deſire only for our uſe; then wee can both poſſeſſe them and loſe them with patience and contented mindes: as wee ſee it was with <hi>Iob,</hi> when hee had loſt all that ever hee had,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iob. 1.20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>hee fell downe upon the ground, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2456:20"/>worſhipped</hi> (or praiſed God) <hi>and ſaid, Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, &amp; naked ſhall I returne thither: the Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away: bleſſed be the name of the Lord. Iob,</hi> when hee was ſtript of all his goods, and ſervants and children, all the ſtore that he had in the world; hee thought of himſelfe no otherwiſe, then as of one that is <hi>naked</hi> and ſtript of his clothes: and therefore hee endured the loſſe of all with great patience, and praiſed God as well when hee tooke them away, as when he gave them. He remembred that hee came without them into the world, and muſt goe without them out of the world: and therefore thought hee might live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them in the world. And ſo, if the things of the world bee unto us as our clothes which are without us, and not faſtened to out fleſh or glued to our hearts; then with the Apoſtle, we may freely ſay of them
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Philip. 4.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery where and in all things I am inſtructed both to bee full, and to bee hungrie, both to abound, and to ſuffer neede.</hi> But contrariwiſe, if the love of worldly things do enter into our hearts, &amp; ſtick faſt to our ſoules, as the skinne doth to the fleſh, every little pull, that draweth away any of them, will draw away ſo much blood from our hearts veine. See the truth of this in an example or two. The
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mar. 10.17. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>young</hi> man, who as hee had great riches, ſo hee loved them too much, came to Chriſt reſolving to doe any thing, that ſhould bee required, for <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of eternall life:</hi> but when Chriſt once bad him, <hi>goe and ſell all that hee had, and give it to the poore, and hee ſhould have treaſure in heaven: hee was ſad at that ſaying,</hi> as loth to loſe heaven, but more loth to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2456:20"/>part with his lands. And
<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 King. 21.4</note> 
                  <hi>Ahab</hi> was ſick and would <hi>eate no bread,</hi> when hee was denied <hi>Naboths vineyard,</hi> which hee did ſo much deſire. And
<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.23</note> 
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel</hi> was ſo wearie of his life for the diſeſteeme of his <hi>counſell,</hi> that hee <hi>went and hanged himſelfe.</hi> And ſo all thoſe that love the world, and <hi>minde earthly things,</hi> who <hi>make their bellie their God,</hi> or <hi>have their portion in this life;</hi> loſe all their joy, and are even wearie of their lives, if once they bee depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of that which they love. And conſequently, ſuch men can never be free from theſe <hi>immoderate, anxious</hi> and tormenting cares. And therefore if any man deſire to eaſe himſelfe of the <hi>cares</hi> of the world, hee muſt firſt emptie his heart of the <hi>love</hi> of the world.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A ſecond <hi>cauſe</hi> of inordinate cares, is a <hi>feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſtruſt</hi> of Gods providence, and his promiſes made unto vs. For if we durſt truſt Gods word, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Heb. 13.5, 6.</note> he ſaith, <hi>I will never leave thee, neither will I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee:</hi> then as the Apoſtle inferreth in the next verſe, <hi>wee might boldly ſay with our ſelves, The Lord is my helper, and I will not feare what man ſhall doe unto me:</hi> not <hi>feare,</hi> if he ſhould take away my goods, or ſtripp mee of my dignities, or deprive me of my libertie, or bereave mee of my limbs and life. And againe wee might ſay with <hi>David;
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſ. 46.1, 2,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> God is our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge &amp; ſtrength, a verie preſent help in trouble. There fore will wee not feare though the earth be removed, &amp; though the mountaines bee caried into the midſt of the ſea: &amp;c.</hi> Such a man, is like a ſhipp at anchor, which the waves and ſtormes may beate and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but cannot move out of his harbour or ſtation:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2456:21"/>nor needes ſuch a man to bee diſquieted with anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and diſtracting cares, becauſe he hath faſt hold on God, who is the rock of his ſalvation and will not faile him. But if a man dareth not reſt upon Gods providence, nor relie on his promiſes; it is no marvell, if he cling faſt to the world, becauſe hee hath no better ſtay to hold by. And therefore take away his goods, or his health, or his libertie, or his preferments; &amp;c. and hee will thinke as <hi>Micah</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Danites,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iud. 18.24.</note> Te have taken away my Gods; and what have I more?</hi> For his worldly goods, they bee his God, in whom hee doth truſt, and whom hee doth adore. And therefore if wee will bee eaſed of immoderate and anxious cares, wee muſt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome our ſelves to depend and relie vpon God, and to put our truſt in him; and then <hi>the peace of God will preſerve us</hi> in all croſſes.</p>
               <p n="3">III.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>3</label> If wee deſire eaſe of worldly cares, wee muſt ſeriouſly meditate on ſuch things, as may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a reaſonable man to equanimitie and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And for that purpoſe theſe meditations will bee helpfull.</p>
               <p n="1">1 If wee conſider the <hi>ſweet providence</hi> of our good God,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Meditat. </seg>1</label> which is ſuch, as that hee turneth all that we ſuffer, to our greater good. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> telleth the people of Iſrael, that
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Deu. 8.15, 16.</note> 
                  <hi>God led them through the great and terrible wildernes, wherein were firie ſerpents and ſcorpions, and drought, where there was no water, but he brought forth water out of the rock of flint, and fed them with Mannah;</hi> [that is, there was no water, but ſuch as God brought them out of the flint, nor no bread but ſuch as hee rained downe out of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2456:21"/>clouds unto them:] and all this was, <hi>that hee might humble them</hi> [with their wants] <hi>and prove them</hi> [in their wants,] <hi>to doe them good at their later end.</hi> And God himſelfe ſaith of thoſe that were caried away captive, that he
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ier. 24.5.</note> 
                  <hi>had ſent them into the land of the Chaldeans for their good.</hi> In which examples we may ſee, that God turned the penury and the captivity of his people into their greater good. And ſo he doth ſtill, by the greateſt croſſes he worketh us the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt comforts: And that he doth two wayes, or in two reſpects:</p>
               <p n="1">(1) Becauſe hee maketh <hi>temporall</hi> croſſes to bee <hi>ſpirituall</hi> cures unto us: and by the ſmart which he layeth on the outward, he preſerveth the ſoundneſſe of the inner man. For as a skilfull <hi>Phyſician</hi> can by his arte ſo temper ranck poyſons, that hee maketh them ſerve for wholeſome medicines: ſo Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, by his great wiſedome doth ſo order our croſſes, that he maketh them to bee <hi>medicinall</hi> unto us. Sometimes he maketh them like <hi>purgations,</hi> to evacuate our pride and profaneneſſe, and worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vaine glory, and ſuch like corruptions of our ſoules. And ſometimes hee maketh them like <hi>preſervatives,</hi> to keepe us from falling into thoſe or the like ſinnes. And ſometimes againe hee maketh them like <hi>cordials,</hi> to ſtrengthen our decaying gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to animate us to holy duties, to pray more fervently, and to reade and heare Gods word more attentively, and to beare the rod of God more pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, and to performe all holy duties with the more life and alacrity. And for theſe and ſuch like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects <hi>David</hi> ſaid,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.71</note> 
                  <hi>It is good for me that I have beene
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2456:22"/>afflicted, that I might learne thy ſtatutes.</hi> And,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.67</note> 
                  <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was afflicted I went aſtray: but now have I kept thy word.</hi> And ſo, every one of us, may ſay of the afflictions that we have ſuffered, if wee make a right uſe of them, <hi>It is good for mee,</hi> that I was dejected with ſickneſſe, or diſgraced by ſlanderous tongues, or wronged by unjuſt neighbours, or vexed with an unquiet wife, or endamaged in mine eſtate, &amp;c. For by this meanes I have learned to love God the more, and the world and mine owne ſinnes the leſſe. And if we make ſuch wholeſome <hi>medicines</hi> for our ſoules out of the calamities that befall us in the world, wee have little cauſe to vexe our ſelves with care, for that which doth doe us ſo much good.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) God doth many times make our preſent croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to be meanes to prevent future evils, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe might doe us greater prejudice in our worldly eſtate and condition. For example,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ier. 24.8, 9.</note> the Iewes in <hi>Ieremies</hi> time, which eſcaped the captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, remained at home for their greater hurt. For they were <hi>driven into all the kingdomes of the earth,</hi> and were ſo tortured and conſumed there, that they became <hi>a proverb, and a taunt, and a curſe in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi> but thoſe that were taken captives, eſcaped theſe greater evils, and at length were reſtored home againe, and enjoyed their former liberties and lands. And in the like manner God doth many times deale with us alſo. For whereas we grieve at the untimely death of our children, which wee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped ſhould have beene the ſtaffe of our old age, and ſhould have inherited both our names and houſes: yet we may obſerve, that many children of as good
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2456:22"/>hope, as they ever were, have proved ſuch croſſes to their parents, as that their fathers or mothers have not ſtuck to ſay of them: <hi>Would God hee had never beene borne,</hi> thus to afflict his friends, and vndoe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: or, I would I had caried him to his grave, when I brought him to his nurſe. Surely <hi>Rachel,</hi> who out of her deſire of children ſaid,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 30.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Give mee children, or elſe I dye:</hi> did afterward
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 35.19.</note> die indeed by child-bearing. And that ſonne which ſhe
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 30.24.</note> joyed to think on aforehand, proved afterward a
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Gen. 35.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Benoni,</hi> a ſonne of her ſorow. And ſo the children, whoſe life we do ſo immoderately deſire, and for whoſe death we grieve without meaſure, had they lived, might have proved <hi>ſonnes of ſorow,</hi> and ſuch as wee would have wiſhed, that they had beene buried long before. And againe, we think it an heavy caſe, if a man be diſeaſed or diſmembred, and either full of paine, or deprived of ſome limme: and yet it is not unuſuall, that ſtrength of body, and ſoundneſſe of limmes, do give occaſion of a farre greater miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; ſo that we may ſometimes heare men ſay, <hi>Would God I had beene ſick in my bed,</hi> or I would I had loſt a legge, or an arme, when I went to ſuch a place, or began ſuch a worke. Thirdly, we count it a lamentable thing, if a man bee robbed by theeves, or impoveriſhed by ill debtors, or undermined by cunning Lawyers, or any way brought to penury or diſtreſſe: and yet wee may note it in the world, that many times riches prove
<note n="*" place="margin">Eccles. 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>the hurt of the owners</hi> of them: either they embolden them to ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate attempt that may be their ruine, or they whet others with envy to lay ſnares for their life, or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2456:23"/>one way or other they breed men ſuch woe, that they will ſay of them, <hi>Would God I had beene borne to never a foot of land,</hi> or, I would I had lived as ſuch a Cobler or Water-bearer doth; for then I had eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped theſe miſchiefes, and might have had ſome comfort in my life. And the like may bee ſaid of other the like caſes; concerning all which wee muſt conſider, that what we ſee afterward, and wiſh for it, when it is too late; that God ſeeth aforehand, and provideth for it, before it come. And hence we may have a good meditation to comfort us in all diſtreſſes. For if God do take away our children that are deare unto us, as our lifes, we ſhould think, It is perhaps becauſe he foreſeeth, that if they ſhould ſurvive, they would work either woe to us, or ruine to themſelves. And if he lay ſickneſſe, or lameneſſe, or maimedneſſe upon our bodies; it may bee hee doth it, becauſe he foreſeeth that if wee had health and ſtrength, and ſoundneſſe of limmes, they would be an occaſion of ſome greater miſchiefe. And if he ſend us want and poverty, and loſſes in our eſtates and dealings, it is becauſe hee foreſeeth that wealth would breede us more woe, then it is worth. But ſure it is, that moſt times God doth lay afflictions, either becauſe hee will procure us ſome good, or prevent ſome evill by them. And if ſo, why ſhould we mourne or take thought for that which tendeth to our welfare and greater comfort?</p>
               <p n="2">2 A ſecond <hi>meditation,</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Meditat. </seg>2</label> to worke patience and to mitigate cares, is, if wee conſider the <hi>times</hi> and <hi>ſeaſons</hi> that God taketh for delivering and relieving of his ſervants. And that is this, that when all other
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2456:23"/>helps faile, then God is moſt ready to help: and then is he neareſt to relieve, when men are neareſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hannah</hi>) <hi>bringeth downe to the grave, and bringeth up againe.</hi> And
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Deut. 32.36</note> 
                  <hi>God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>) <hi>will judge his people, and repent himſelfe for his ſervants; when he ſeeth that their power is gone, and there is none ſhut up, or left.</hi> And he (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>)
<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.6.</note> 
                  <hi>comforteth thoſe that be caſt downe.</hi> And hee (ſaith
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 68.5. &amp; Pſal. 10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>David)</hi> is <hi>a Father of the fatherleſſe, and a Iudge of the widowes.</hi> And,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 27.10.</note> 
                  <hi>When my father and mother for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me, then the Lord will take me up.</hi> In all which ſayings wee may conſider two things: (1) Gods great mercy in helping the diſtreſſed: <hi>hee bringeth men up out of the grave,</hi> he <hi>judgeth</hi> his people, that is, he righteth them from their adverſaries, and he is a <hi>Father</hi> to pity them, and a <hi>Iudge</hi> to defend their juſt cauſe. (2) The objects of this mercy, or who they be that God ſends ſuch help unto; and they be thoſe who are <hi>brought downe to the grave,</hi> that is, who are in the deepeſt miſery: and, thoſe whoſe <hi>power is gone,</hi> that is, who have no meanes to help themſelves; and thoſe, who <hi>are caſt downe,</hi> who are <hi>fatherleſſe or widowes,</hi> and who are <hi>forſaken of their parents</hi> and neareſt kinred, and are deſtitute of all friends and helpers. And hereby wee may ſee, that God doth eſpecially ſhew mercy, when men are in the greateſt miſerie. And that hee doth upon three grounds, or for three cauſes. (1) Becauſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth to ſhew mercy, and <hi>mercy</hi> ſtill hath <hi>miſery</hi> for its object, and is then moſt ready, when there is the greateſt need. And from hence it is, that when the Iſraelites were oppreſſed by the Egyptians,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2456:24"/>and
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Exod. 2.23.</note> 
                  <hi>ſighed by reaſon of the bondage, and cryed;</hi> then <hi>their cry came up unto God by reaſon of the bondage.</hi> That which made them to <hi>cry,</hi> made him to <hi>help;</hi> that is, the ſore bondage which they ſuffered. And
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Exo. 22.23.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou afflict the widow and the fatherleſſe</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and they cry unto me; I will ſurely heare their cry.</hi> And it is given for a reaſon of Gods ſpeciall mercy towards Iſrael,
<note n="*" place="margin">2 King. 14.26.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe he ſaw the affliction of Iſrael, that it was very bitter: for there was not any ſhut up, nor any left, nor any helper for Iſrael.</hi> The meaning is, as I take it, that there was none <hi>left</hi> and reſerved from the common calamity, nor any other that might help them in this miſery. (2) Becauſe God hath a ſpeciall <hi>communion</hi> with his people, ſo that
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſay 63.9.</note> 
                  <hi>in all their affliction</hi> hee profeſſeth himſelfe to <hi>be afflicted:</hi> and that
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Acts 9.4.</note> 
                  <hi>he that perſecuteth them, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth him:</hi> and that
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Zach. 2.8.</note> he who <hi>toucheth them, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the apple of his eye:</hi> And therefore, the more they are afflicted, the more himſelfe ſuffereth in them: and conſequently, the readier he will be both to ſuccour them, and to eaſe himſelfe. (3) Becauſe when men are deſtitute of all help and hope, and have neither friends, nor meanes; then God may gaine the greateſt honour by their deliverance: for it will then appeare to bee his worke. So S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelfe and <hi>Timothy,</hi> that they were
<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.8, 9</note> 
                  <hi>preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of meaſure, above ſtrength, in ſo much that they deſpaired even of life;</hi> and that therefore they <hi>had the ſentence of death in themſelves, that they ſhould not truſt in themſelves, but in God, which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the dead.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that God reſuſed to free him from the buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fettings
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2456:24"/>of Satan at the preſent, becauſe
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> 
                  <hi>his ſtrength was made perfect in weakneſſe.</hi> And wee reade of <hi>Gedcon,</hi> that God would not ſave him from his enemies by an armie of two and thirty thouſand men, but he did ſave him by three hundred. And the reaſon is given in the text,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iudg. 7.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Leſt Iſrael ſhould vaunt themſelves againſt God, and ſay, Mine owne hand hath ſaved me.</hi> The meaning is, that if they ſhould have conquered, when they had a great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, they might have aſcribed the victory to their owne ſtrength: but if with an handfull of men, they ſhould overcome a great hoſte of enemies; all men might ſee that it was Gods doing, and not their owne endeuour that got them the victorie. And thus God doth uſe to doe ſtill; hee leaveth men to ſtruggle with the croſſe, when their wants are but ſmall, and the meanes competent to provide againſt them: but mans <hi>extremity</hi> is Gods <hi>opportunity;</hi> when they have no power, then hee ſheweth his; and when all helps and hopes from men do faile them, then is he ready with reliefe from heaven, that his power and ſtrength and mercy may bee ſeene. And hence we have an excellent <hi>meditation</hi> of great comfort. For if our diſtreſſe be <hi>ſmall,</hi> our care for it ſhould not be <hi>great:</hi> and if our caſe grow <hi>deſperate,</hi> and remedileſſe in reſpect of humane help; then <hi>the Iudge is at the doores,</hi> and then God is even at hand, to relieve us, and then may wee comfort our droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſoules, as the Apoſtle did the afflicted He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Heb. 10.37.</note> 
                  <hi>Yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come and will not tary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Meditat. </seg>3</label> it will not be unprofitable for eaſing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2456:25"/>of cares, if amidſt the evils that we ſuffer, wee call to minde the <hi>good things,</hi> which by Gods mercy wee do enjoy: and if, as we weigh our croſſes by think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the greatneſſe or grievouſneſſe of them; ſo we lay in the other ſcale over againſt them, the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that are ſtill continued unto us. For ſo wee may finde perhaps, that our bleſſings do overweigh our croſſes; and therefore that we have greater cauſe to praiſe God that we are ſo well dealt with, then to grudge or grieve that we are no better. For example, ſay that wee are <hi>ſick,</hi> or ſore, or maimed: yet wee have meate, and phyſick, and attendance, and a ſoft lodging, which many others as good as our ſelves do want. Or, wee are <hi>oppreſſed</hi> with great ones, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermined by Conie-catchers, or ſlandered by foule mouthes: yet we have ſome kinde friends to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortus, and an obſequious family to obſerve us, and a commodious houſe to dwell in; al which may refreſh us at home, when we have beene moleſted abroad. Or againe, wee are <hi>impeveriſhed</hi> in our eſtates, and want meanes and maintenance, and wee are croſſed in our preferments, and ſuffer repulſe in our ſuites, and are deſtitute of friends to ſupplie us: but wee have ſoundnes of limmes, health of bodie, and a right and readie uſe of our ſenſes; ſo that wee can endure labour, or ſerve in ſome places of employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and worke for the getting of an honeſt living. Or yet againe, ſay wee have <hi>all theſe</hi> croſſes, and none of the other comforts (though who can ſay ſo truly?) yet we have the comfort of Gods word, and peace of conſcience, and hope of eternall life, and wee have God our father to protect us, and Chriſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2456:25"/>our Redeemer to pray for us, and the holy Spirit of them both to comfort us, and the bleſſed Angels to pitch their tents round about us, and to guard us: Or if wee have not theſe for our comfort, it is our fault alone that we want them; and then wee have greater cauſe to bee ſolicitous and carefull for the obtaining of theſe ſpirituall mercies, then for the repairing of our worldly wants. And hence wee have a <hi>meditation</hi> of great comfort: For if wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our worldly ſtate, wee are not without the teſtimonies of Gods love towards us in many things: but if wee looke upon our meanes of grace, and our hopes of glory, and Gods eternall favour in Chriſt, then we have greater cauſe to cheare our ſelves againſt all worldly troubles. For then as God comforted his people, ſaying,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſai 30.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Though the Lord give you the bread of adverſitie, and the water of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; yet ſhall not thy Teachers bee removed into a corner any more; but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy Teachers, and thine eares ſhall heare a word behinde thee ſaying, This is the way, walke ye in it.</hi> So may euery afflicted Chriſtian comfort himſelfe in the like manner, Though the Lord have given mee, <hi>bread of adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> and <hi>waters of affliction,</hi> though hee have laid on me ſicknes, or wants, or diſgraces, or ſuch like; yet hee hath not taken from mee his Word, his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his Miniſters; meanes of grace, or peace of conſcience, or the light of his countenance: and ſo I may have theſe, it is no great matter though I want all other things. For as <hi>David</hi> ſaid,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 4.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon us:</hi> and then addeth, <hi>Thou haſt put gladnes in my heart, more
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2456:26"/>then in the time that their corne and their wine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed:</hi> ſo the Chriſtian ſoule may ſay, God hath put more cauſe of gladnes in my heart, by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of his favour, and the expectation of his glorie, then if I had had corne and wine and oile, honours and offices and preferments, health and ſtrength and libertie, and whatſoever elſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the outward man.</p>
               <p n="4">4 It may help to alaie our cares for the world,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Meditat. </seg>4</label> if wee conſider how God hath <hi>alaied</hi> and <hi>tempered</hi> theſe verie croſſes, whereof wee complaine. For ſay, that God hath ſtricken us with ſicknes: yes; but hee might juſtly have ſtricken us with death. Or hee hath laied loſſes and wants upon us: yes; but hee might have left us without any ragge to our backs, or crumme of bread for our bellies, or a dropp of water to relieve our thirſt. Or hee hath ſuffered men to oppreſſe us, and hale us into priſon: yes; but he might have given way to the Devill, to ſet upon us, and hurrie us into hell. And finally, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever wee ſuffer, yet it is a great deale leſſe then wee have deſerved, and then God might have laied upon us, if he had rewarded us according to our ſins. And hence wee may have a good <hi>meditation</hi> for our comfort. For in what diſtreſſes ſoever wee bee, yet wee may bee glad that they are no worſe. And if our croſſes ſeeme grievous to bee borne, wee may cheare our ſelves in the Apoſtles words,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.8, 9</note> 
                  <hi>Wee are troubled on every ſide, yet not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed; wee are perplexed, but not in deſpaire; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, but not forſaken; caſt downe, but not deſtroyed.</hi> When <hi>Hezekiah</hi> conſidered this, hee praiſed God
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2456:26"/>for it:
<note n="(d)" place="margin">King. 20.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Good</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>is the word of the Lord which thou haſt ſpoken:</hi> and, <hi>Is it not good if peace and truth bee in my dayes?</hi> which is as if hee ſhould have ſaid, God might juſtly have laied this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both on mee and my children; and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie it is that doth ſpare mee in mine owne perſon, and deferre his judgment till afterward. And the Church in the Lamentations,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Lam. 3.22.</note> 
                  <hi>It is of the Lords mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that wee are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſsions faile not.</hi> And ſo conſidering that all our croſſes are farre leſſe then our ſinnes, and that God hath ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led much mercie in our afflictions, wee have great cauſe to bleſſe God, that our <hi>ſufferings</hi> are ſo caſie, when our <hi>deſervings</hi> have beene ſo badd.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Fiftly and laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Meditat. </seg>5</label> amidſt our ſolicitous cares for the world, we may thinke, whether we have not greater cauſe of <hi>taking thought</hi> for our <hi>ſoules,</hi> which yet doth ſeldome and little trouble our mindes. For example, ſay we have loſt our goods, or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſome great man, or endangered our liberties and lives; and this filleth us with anxietie and care: Yea, but have wee not loſt ſome meaſure of Gods Spirit, or offended the Lord of heaven, and endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered our ſoules and ſalvation? And where is the thought that we take for theſe things? This <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation</hi> may either ſerve to ſhame us for our world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindednes, and that wee have ſo much care about theſe tranſitorie things: or it may ſerve to worke in us a greater care for our ſoules; and if that once bee increaſed, our care for the world will in a like proportion be decreaſed with it.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the <hi>Meditations,</hi> with which if we buſie our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2456:27"/>ſelves, when occaſion ſhall require; they may help to avert our minds from muſing on our worldly griefe, and may mitigate thoſe cares that doe too much poſſeſſe our hearts. And thus much may ſerve for this third rule, which is to meditate on ſuch things, as may perſwade to patience and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quanimitie.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>4</label> A fourth and laſt rule is, that in all our penſive thoughts wee <hi>goe to God</hi> for comfort, and ſtill unloade our cares into his boſome by praier and ſupplication. For if wee caſt them upon God, God will eaſe us of them. Nor will any man think, that hath not tryed it, how much this courſe may availe to the quieting of a diſtracted ſoule; and that either becauſe having done his dutie, hee may comfort his heart with the conſcience of it; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe having referred himſelfe to Gods mercie, hee may well hope that God will ſupport him. But what ever the reaſon bee, certaine it is that <hi>Hannah</hi> gained great eaſe by it. It is ſaid of her
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Sa. 1.6, 7, 8</note> that being upbraided by her adverſarie for her bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe, <hi>ſhe wept, and did not eate, and her heart was grieved.</hi> Here was her care and thought-taking for want of children. But then
<note n="(b)" place="margin">ver. 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>in the bitterneſſe of her ſoule, ſhe went and prayed unto the Lord, and wept ſore.</hi> Here <hi>Hannah</hi> caſt her <hi>burden</hi> upon the Lord, and unloaded her cares into his boſom. And then third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is added after all, that having done her prayers,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">ver. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhe went her way, and did eate, and her countenance was no more ſad.</hi> Where wee may ſee, that ſhee had no ſooner prayed, but ſhe was cheared: ſhe had caſt her burden upon God, and that caſed her heart. And
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2456:27"/>ſo if wee by hearty prayer caſt our burden upon God, that will bee a readie way to unburden our ſelves. And therefore, when cares take hold on us, in ſtead of muſing, wee ſhould fall to praying. And then
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Philip. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>the peace of God, which paſſeth all underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding will preſerve our hearts and mindes through Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe bee the <hi>Rules;</hi> it now remaineth to applic and make uſe of them for our ſelves. And that wee may doe two waies.</p>
               <p n="1">1 If wee have any <hi>cares</hi> upon us alreadie, wee have hence direction how to <hi>worke</hi> them out: and that is by <hi>oppoſing</hi> them, as they do ariſe, and by <hi>diverting</hi> our thoughts upon better objects, and by <hi>conſidering</hi> what end the Lord maketh of ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; and laſtly by <hi>unloading</hi> our cares into Gods boſom by ſupplication and prayer. And if thus wee finde not preſent eaſe, yet wee muſt ſtill waite: for many have miſſed of help, becauſe they have made too much haſte. Of <hi>Abraham</hi> wee heard before, that hee tooke his ſonne, and the knife and the wood and the fire, and went his three dayes journey, that hee might ſacrifice his ſonne, where God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed: and after hee had gone all the way, and ſtaied all the time, and was now at the laſt caſt of killing his ſonne; then (and not till then) hee found Gods help in the topp of the mount. But now ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that <hi>Abraham,</hi> either wearied with the jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or ouercome with griefe, or deſpairing of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture help, had turned back againe after a dayes jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or two; Or ſay, hee had ſate himſelfe downe at the foote of the hill, and with impatient cries had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2456:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2456:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2456:29"/>bemoaned his uncomfortable condition, what may we thinke would the iſſue have beene? Sure, it may well bee ſuppoſed, that by detaining his ſonne, he might have loſt him: but certaine it is, that by ſtaying at the <hi>foote</hi> of the hill, he had not found God in the <hi>topp</hi> of the mount. And ſo, if wee make too much haſte, and will not expect Gods time, wee may outrunne Gods providence, and faile of his protection and mercie. But if wee holde on, in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the meanes, and reſting on Gods worde; wee ſhall in the end finde the Proverb to bee true, <hi>In the mountaine will the Lord be ſeene.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 If dangers bee towards, (and when are they not?) wee may hereby learne how to <hi>prepare</hi> for them, and how to <hi>arme</hi> againſt them, that they may not affect us with immoderate cares, when they come. And that is, that wee ſetle our ſelves aforehand ſo to deale in all our occaſions, as the wiſe husbandman dealeth in his buſineſſe. He diggeth, and dungeth, and ploweth and ſoweth; and when hee hath done his daies worke, betaketh himſelfe to his nights reſt, and leaveth the growing of the corne, and the ordering of the weather to Gods care, and providence. And ſo ſhould wee reſolve to doe. For example thus; If ſickneſſe ſhall befall us, wee will goe to the Phyſician for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and uſe ſuch druggs and diet as may bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and provide ſuch Attendants as may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply us with neceſſaries; and this is as the ſowing of our ſeede: and when this is once done, then we have done our dayes worke; and therefore will laie our ſelves downe in peace, and let God alone
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2456:29"/>with the iſſue, in whoſe hands only it is. And the like courſe wee ſhould reſolve upon, in all other the like caſes; if wee ſhall bee ſlandered by foule mouths, undermined by cunning heads, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by potent neighbours, endamaged in our worldly eſtates, or whatſoever other croſſe wee ſhall meete with; wee will firſt ſow our ſeede, and then take our reſt; firſt uſe good meanes, and then truſt God with the ſucceſſe: and hee that hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed help, before wee did aske; will not faile to peforme it, when wee thinke not on it. And if thus wee prepare our ſelves, before the croſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; wee ſhall be the more free from cares, when it is come. For nothing is more availeable, then courage in ſuch caſes; and a reſolution aforehand, will by Gods help make us ſtedfaſt, when the ſtorme is upon us: nor will God bee wanting to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us his help, if wee bee not wanting in uſing of the meanes. For that belongeth to us alſo, which was ſpoken to <hi>Solomon; Vp &amp; be doing:
<note place="margin">1 Chron. 22.16.</note> and the Lord will bee with thee.</hi> Now the God of all mercie, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, guide our hearts in the doing of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and bleſſe our labours with ſucceſſe and comfort, and ſo free us from cares of the world, that we may ſerve him without diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction all our dayes. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:2456:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:2456:30"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
